Okay, it's the modern era, and that
means the phenomenon of globalization
changed the US economy in all kinds of
ways, and I reckon you ought to know
about it. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so before we get crazy talking
about globalization and its effects on
the US economy, I need to start by
telling you about the various new
technologies that facilitated this
change. And take heart, my dear pupil,
because the concepts that are about to
pour forth from my mouth hole might be
the first time in this whole course
where you're like, "By the hammer of
Thor, I've heard of this stuff." And on
that account, because I'm so excited for
you, to give you three examples of
modern technology that facilitated
globalization. First of all, we have
computers. Now, the first computers were
developed by the US military for use
during World War II, and even though
they performed relatively elementary
tasks, these machines filled entire
honking rooms. And if you've ever ridden
Spaceship Earth in Epcot, then baby, you
already know that. But anyway, by the
1970s, American innovators had developed
microchips that enabled computers to be
built at a fraction of the size. And
then, folks like Steve Jobs and Steve
Wozniak adapted this technology in order
to build desktop computers, not for
military applications, but for personal
and business use, or the getting
dysentery on the Oregon Trail use. And
so, in 1984, they introduced the Apple
Macintosh, which was widely adopted
across American businesses and homes.
And as the microchip technology advanced
more and more, they were used to power
even the most basic appliances like
televisions and telephones. And that was
real nice and all, but it was the second
big technology combined with computers
that accelerated the crap out of
globalization. And that second
technology would be the internet. So,
just like computers, the first iteration
of the internet was developed in the
United States in the 1960s as a way to
share both military and scientific data.
But by the 1990s, the technology had
been developed to the point where it was
more affordable to the average citizen.
And therefore, with the concurrent rise
of personal computers, the 1990s gave us
the World Wide Web. And by the turn of
the millennium, the internet was
responsible for connecting the world's
population through email and connecting
businesses with their customers in a
pattern that accelerated the global
phenomenon of communication and
commerce. And speaking of the internet,
you're on the internet right now, and
wouldn't you know it, so am I. And you
know what else is on the internet? My A
push Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to help you get an A
in your class and a five on your exam in
May. And if that's something you're
into, that link is in the description.
Okay, and finally, the third development
that fostered globalization was the rise
of cellular technology. So, as you may
recall, the telephone was invented way
back in 1876, and though it was too
expensive for most people, the societal
elites took advantage of the ability to
talk to other people across great
distances. And while more and more
Americans adopted telephones as they
became cheaper, the technology basically
remained unchanged until the 1980s when
cellular technology was introduced,
which enabled connectivity through the
air. And with the rapid development of
cell phones, people could talk to other
people across the world no matter their
location. Okay, so we had our dessert
first, and now let's munch on the main
meat of this topic, and that's how
globalization fundamentally changed the
US economy. So, as I mentioned in the
last video, global relationships during
the Cold War were often characterized by
economic and political rivalry, not to
mention a metric buttload of doomsday
weapons pointed at each other's faces.
But after the Cold War, that kind of
rivalry was increasingly replaced by
cooperation and an emphasis on free
market competition. And the main driver
of this change was the phenomenon of
globalization, which refers to the
increasing interdependence of all
countries' economies on one another. So,
two world wars accelerated this kind of
relationship building among the
international community, but after the
end of the Cold War, the economic
emphasis of global cooperation became a
key part of the role of the United
States in the world. And one major cause
of this shift was the growing emphasis
on neoliberal economic policies in
several major world states. Now,
neoliberalism refers to an economic
emphasis on free market policies, and
that includes lowering trade barriers
and the deregulation of industries and
the transfer of public sector industries
to private parties. And if you'll
recall, it was Ronald Reagan who
championed neoliberal economic policies
in the United States, including sweeping
tax cuts and the deregulation of
businesses. But Reagan was part of a
larger cadre of world leaders who were
pushing for this very change. For
example, Margaret Thatcher, the Prime
Minister of the United Kingdom, likewise
implemented similar policies, and to a
lesser degree, so did Deng Xiaoping in
China. So, Deng rose to power after the
death of Mao Zedong, and he led China's
government to relax its grip on the
tightly controlled economy under Mao's
communist regime. And as a result,
international corporations like
McDonald's and Toyota and Coca-Cola
began doing business in China, and by
2014, foreign businesses accounted for
about half of China's imports and
exports. And then, the second major
cause for the acceleration of a
globalized economy included advances in
digital communications technologies. And
since I already told you about all those
in the beginning, let's move on to the
effects of globalization, and there are
three big ones that you need to know.
First of all, globalization
fundamentally restructured global
economic activity. What I mean is, for
several centuries before this period,
the most powerful nations in the world
were those that had industrialized. And
one of the main features of that
industrialization is that the factories
and all the laborers who made those
factories work were located within the
country itself. But beginning in the
1970s, the cost of domestic
manufacturing began to increase
significantly, and corporate investment
into factory infrastructure no longer
seemed to be a good investment, and this
development led to a new global
distribution of work, and here's how
that played out. So, wealthier, more
developed countries like the United
States became more characterized by
knowledge workers whose main capital for
work was not their bodies, but rather
their minds. And then, manufacturing, on
the other hand, was now increasingly
located in developing countries where
international businesses could save
money by paying lower wages to foreign
workers than was legal in their own
country. So, as a result of big American
corporations outsourcing their
manufacturing outfits to other
countries, many industrial workers lost
their jobs. And as the numbers of
America's industrial workers declined,
so too did the membership and power of
labor unions decline. And then, the
second economic effect of globalization
is directly related to the first, which
is to say, a growing income inequality
across the United States. So, one of the
major effects of this whole economic
reordering and the decline of union
membership was a persistent stagnation
of wages among the working and middle
classes. However, on the whole, the
1990s was a relatively prosperous era as
American corporations benefited
significantly from the increased revenue
that came as a result of globalization.
But rather than contributing to a
generalized prosperity among Americans,
these factors actually contributed to a
growing wealth gap. You see, while
middle class and working class wages
stagnated, the excess wealth generated
by American productivity was mainly
funneled into the pockets of the richest
Americans. In fact, in the first decade
of the 21st century, the wealthiest 1%
of Americans held a third of the
country's wealth. And finally, the third
big effect of globalization was the rise
of global economic institutions. So,
after World War II ended, it became
abundantly clear that no country in the
world was an island unto themselves. Uh,
what about Madagascar? Shut up, it was a
metaphor. What I mean is, in a
globalized world, no country could exist
in complete isolation from other
countries. Like all nations of the world
were now, for better or worse, becoming
increasingly dependent on one another.
And so, that led to the rise of many
transnational organizations like the
United Nations that were established to
help foster cooperation in a globalized
world. And some of those organizations
were created to help countries develop
economic relationships, and such was the
case with the World Trade Organization,
which exists to regulate trade on a
global scale. Essentially, the WTO
promotes global trade by assisting in
the negotiation of trade deals, acting
as a moderator for various trade
disputes, and creating initiatives to
assist developing countries along the
scale of development. And President Bill
Clinton worked to link the United States
closely with the work of the WTO in
order to facilitate American trade
worldwide. And in part, because WTO
policies tend to favor wealthier
countries like the United States, the
value of American exports increased
nearly 10% by the year 2000. So, after
1980, US involvement in the
globalization of the world's economy
fundamentally and forever changed the
way American economics played out. Okay,
you can click here to watch my other
unit nine videos, or you can click here
to grab my A push Heimler review guide,
which has everything you need to help
you get a five on your exam in May. I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch on
the flip flop. Heimler out.